{
  "title": "Computer_Network - Computer_Network — Slot 1 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Computer_Network — Slot 1",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Suppose we are transmitting frames between two nodes using the Stop-and-Wait protocol. The frame size is 3000 bits. The transmission rate of the channel is 2000 bps (bits/second) and the propagation delay between the two nodes is 100 milliseconds. Assume that the processing times at the source and destination are negligible. Also, assume that the size of the acknowledgment packet is negligible.\nWhich ONE of the following most accurately gives the channel utilization for the above scenario in percentage? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>88.23</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>93.75</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>85.44</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>66.67</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>88.23</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460809/gate-cse-2025-set-2-question-26#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Consider a network that uses Ethernet and IPv4. Assume that IPv4 headers do not use any options field. Each Ethernet frame can carry a maximum of 1500 bytes in its data field. A UDP segment is transmitted. The payload (data) in the UDP segment is 7488 bytes.\n<br>\nWhich ONE of the following choices has the CORRECT total number of fragments transmitted and the size of the last fragment including IPv4 header? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>5 fragments, 1488 bytes</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>6 fragments, 88 bytes</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>6 fragments, 108 bytes</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>6 fragments, 116 bytes</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>6 fragments, 116 bytes</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460822/gate-cse-2025-set-2-question-13#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>A machine receives an IPv4 datagram. The protocol field of the IPv4 header has the protocol number of a protocol X.  <br>\nWhich ONE of the following is NOT a possible candidate for X? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Internet Control Message Protocol (ICMP)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Internet Group Management Protocol (IGMP)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Open Shortest Path First (OSPF)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Routing Information Protocol (RIP)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>Routing Information Protocol (RIP)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460827/gate-cse-2025-set-2-question-8#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>Consider the routing protocols given in List I and the names given in List II:\n<br><br>\n\\(\\begin{array}{|c l|c l|}\n\\hline\n\\textbf{List I} &amp; &amp; \\textbf{List II} &amp; \\\\\n\\hline\n\\text{(i)} &amp; \\text{Distance vector routing} &amp; \\text{(a)} &amp; \\text{Bellman-Ford} \\\\\n\\hline\n\\text{(ii)} &amp; \\text{Link state routing} &amp; \\text{(b)} &amp; \\text{Dijkstra} \\\\\n\\hline\n\\end{array}\n\\)<br><br>\nFor matching of items in List I with those in List II, which ONE of the following options is CORRECT? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>(i) - (a) and (ii) - (b)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>(i) - (a) and (ii) - (a)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>(i) - (b) and (ii) - (a)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>(i) - (b) and (ii) - (b)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>(i) - (a) and (ii) - (b)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460828/gate-cse-2025-set-2-question-7#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following statements:\n<br><br>\n(i) Address Resolution Protocol (ARP) provides a mapping from an IP address to the corresponding hardware (link-layer) address.\n<br>\n(ii) A single TCP segment from a sender S to a receiver R cannot carry both data from S to R and acknowledgement for a segment from R to S.\n<br><br>\nWhich ONE of the following is CORRECT? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Both (i) and (ii) are TRUE</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>(i) is TRUE and (ii) is FALSE</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>(i) is FALSE and (ii) is TRUE</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Both (i) and (ii) are FALSE</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>(i) is TRUE and (ii) is FALSE</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460829/gate-cse-2025-set-2-question-6#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>Suppose a message of size 15000 bytes is transmitted from a source to a destination using IPv4 protocol via two routers as shown in the figure. Each router has a defined maximum transmission unit (MTU) as shown in the figure, including IP header. The number of fragments that will be delivered to the destination is _________. (Answer in integer)\n<br><img style=\"max-width:50%;height:auto;border-radius:8px;\" data-lazyloaded=\"1\" decoding=\"async\" src=\"images\\gatePYQ\\Computer_Network\\q47_cddf7a5f.webp\"><br> <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "7",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460033/gate-cse-2025-set-1-question-47#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>A packet with the destination IP address 145.36.109.70 arrives at a router whose routing table is shown. Which interface will the packet be forwarded to?\n<br>    \\(\\begin{array}{|c|c|c|}\n\\hline\n\\textbf{Subnet Address} &amp; \\textbf{Subnet Mask (in CIDR notation)} &amp; \\textbf{Interface} \\\\\n\\hline\n145.36.0.0 &amp; /16 &amp; E1 \\\\\n\\hline\n145.36.128.0 &amp; /17 &amp; E2 \\\\\n\\hline\n145.36.64.0 &amp; /18 &amp; E3 \\\\\n\\hline\n145.36.255.0 &amp; /24 &amp; E4 \\\\\n\\hline\n\\text{Default} &amp; -- &amp; E5 \\\\\n\\hline\n\\end{array}\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(E3\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(E1\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(E2\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(E5\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(E3\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460050/gate-cse-2025-set-1-question-30#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>Consider the 3-way handshaking protocol for TCP connection establishment. Let the three packets exchanged during the connection establishment be denoted as P1, P2, and P3, in order. Which of the following option(s) is/are TRUE with respect to TCP header flags that are set in the packets? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "multiple",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>P3: SYN = 1, ACK = 1</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>P2: SYN = 1, ACK = 1</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>P2: SYN = 0, ACK = 1</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>P1: SYN = 1</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": [
            "<b>B.</b> <p>P2: SYN = 1, ACK = 1</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>P1: SYN = 1</p>"
          ],
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460068/gate-cse-2025-set-1-question-12#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Identify the ONE CORRECT matching between the OSI layers and their corresponding functionalities as shown.\n<br>\n\\(\\begin{array}{|l|l|}\n\\hline\n\\textbf{OSI Layers} &amp; \\textbf{Functionalities} \\\\\n\\hline\n\\text{(a) Network layer} &amp; \\text{(I) Packet routing} \\\\\n\\hline\n\\text{(b) Transport layer} &amp; \\text{(II) Framing and error handling} \\\\\n\\hline\n\\text{(c) Datalink layer} &amp; \\text{(III) Host to host communication} \\\\\n\\hline\n\\end{array}\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>(a)-(I), (b)-(II), (c)-(III)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>(a)-(I), (b)-(III), (c)-(II)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>(a)-(II), (b)-(I), (c)-(III)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>(a)-(III), (b)-(II), (c)-(I)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>(a)-(I), (b)-(III), (c)-(II)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460074/gate-cse-2025-set-1-question-6#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Consider an Ethernet segment with a transmission speed of \\(10^8\\) bits/sec and a\nmaximum segment length of 500 meters. If the speed of propagation of the signal\nin the medium is \\(2 \\times 10^8\\) meters/sec, then the minimum frame size (in bits) required\nfor collision detection is _________ <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "500",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422852/gate-cse-2024-set-2-question-45#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>Consider a TCP connection operating at a point of time with the congestion window\nof size 12 MSS (Maximum Segment Size), when a timeout occurs due to packet\nloss. Assuming that all the segments transmitted in the next two RTTs (Round Trip\nTime) are acknowledged correctly, the congestion window size (in MSS) during the\nthird RTT will be _________ <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "4",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422853/gate-cse-2024-set-2-question-44#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Which  one  of  the  following  CIDR  prefixes  exactly  represents  the  range  of IP addresses 10.12.2.0 to 10.12.3.255? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>10.12.2.0/23</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>10.12.2.0/24</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>10.12.0.0/22</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>10.12.2.0/22</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>10.12.2.0/23</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422869/gate-cse-2024-set-2-question-28#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following fields of an IP header is/are always modified by any router before it forwards the IP packet? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Source IP Address</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Protocol</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Time to Live (TTL)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Header Checksum</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Time to Live (TTL)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422875/gate-cse-2024-set-2-question-22#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>Which of the following statements about IPv4 fragmentation is/are TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>The fragmentation of an IP datagram is performed only at the source of the datagram</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>The fragmentation of an IP datagram is performed at any IP router which finds that the size of the datagram to be transmitted exceeds the MTU</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>The reassembly of fragments is performed only at the destination of the datagram</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>The reassembly of fragments is performed at all intermediate routers along the path from the source to the destination</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>The fragmentation of an IP datagram is performed at any IP router which finds that the size of the datagram to be transmitted exceeds the MTU</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422879/gate-cse-2024-set-2-question-18#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>Node X has a TCP connection open to node Y. The packets from X to Y go through\nan intermediate IP router R. Ethernet switch S is the first switch on the network path\nbetween X and R. Consider a packet sent from X to Y over this connection.<br>\nWhich of the following statements is/are TRUE about the destination IP and MAC\naddresses on this packet at the time it leaves X? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>The destination IP address is the IP address of R</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>The destination IP address is the IP address of Y</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>The destination MAC address is the MAC address of S</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>The destination MAC address is the MAC address of Y</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>The destination IP address is the IP address of Y</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422884/gate-cse-2024-set-2-question-13#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}